okay I'm speaking with Dan Schweitzer of
New York holographic Laboratories how
are you doing Dan I'm very fine Frank
how are you I'm doing good thank you I
want to thank you very much for taking
the time to come on the show thank you
first before we get started on anything
I want to I want to congratulate you for
the great things that you've been doing
here with this uh talk show I oh thank
you very compelling and I think it's
been great for holography I love your
spirit and uh I'm just totally in uh in
awe of uh all you've managed to
accomplish in the past year or two it's
been quite amazing well I'm a real nut
case you must see
welcome to the nutcase yeah I know the
listeners are going to be very happy to
hear you on here one of the things
that's nice about the show is the fact
that there's probably so many people out
there who have read about your work have
been able to see your work in galleries
in different places and also all the
things that's been written about you and
the different books out there
photography and here and you're pretty
lucky and one of the things I guess that
that just leads me into the fact that
you're I know I've I read about you
probably when I was back in high school
in books on hologography we've all seen
so many people come and go in this field
what do you credit your longevity to
[Laughter]
gee what a list
think it's just the passion for
holography I think it just keeps me
buoyed up whatever I think I'm I'm
losing it I I think about what it is
that we're doing here and I I get uh I
get re-inspired and I just keep pushing
pushes because I believe in it so
intensely in so many of its different
levels of application your lab was
around I would say early 70s or before
yeah the it's it's a not to belabor the
the historical side of it but um
the lab that uh Sam Moray and I started
in 1970 76.
it's really uh basically having taken
over the the New York school of
holography which began in 1972 72 where
I was
and learned myself did Jodie Burns was
he involved with that or anything
absolutely right Jody Burns it was it
was totally inspired at the time and got
the ball rolling for a lot
to him that I owe the greatest amount of
gratitude for having gotten me started
on my my background was in the theater
and film oh yes yes so uh for me it was
really quite a quite a Looking Glass
experience falling into it and we all
probably feel the same way that we're
still doing it getting in on the ground
floor of what we know to be uh
what was the attraction
I you know it was a different time back
then well it was a different time
absolutely there was it it was
interesting that in the courses that I
took very few of us knew really
I learned from people who only had just
recently learned themselves
and so there was a lot of exploration a
lot of Discovery going on in those days
every time you did something and it's
still the same way you feel like I feel
like you were inventing it for the first
time and that's what keeps it exciting
and fresh yeah you obviously chose to
work with white light transmission
holography was there a reason behind
that pretty much so I think it it
if you could attribute schools for
holography I would say that the New York
for the most part the New York
holographers were of that school of
white light transmission perhaps because
of uh
Steve in the early days he conducted a
course
uh two courses actually in Rainbow
allography in the early days we were all
very curious about it the
reason that it appealed most to me I
think was that it was not so much
documentation or I see reflection
holography very often as being an
incredible form for documenting
existing subjects and I think the appeal
for the rainbow holography was that
doesn't actually document quite as well
as it does allow for you a greater
amount of volume to record viewable
seeing depth front to back
and and it allowed for a different way
of controlling color through the
engineering of the camera as opposed to
the chemistry and the reflection
hologram Yes Yes And So It came it
became much more like light sculpture
for a loss
the idea of sculpting energy was was
really an extraordinary uh idea from the
start and then clearly that's what what
rainbow holography has sort of become
although not to say that it can't be
used to document it it excels when you
wish to bend and interpret the light
itself it's really quite interesting
you've Incorporated sculpture itself
into some of your pieces right yes I
have I started out by uh by by doing
small sculptures for the content of the
Holograms
and that the culmination of that sort of
venture for me was that it was a
completion of a holographic tryptic and
I did a a triptych hologram of a gallery
of holograms and in each panel there was
there were Holograms inside the Hologram
and in one case there was a hologram was
in a hologram within a hologram within a
hologram photograph yes you know it went
several layers back trying to trying to
increase the depth of the scene and so
forth I think one of the early pieces
that I remember of years when I was
younger
was I believe it was a man sitting at a
desk looking at a window yes yes that's
a very early work it was called
uh it was it was an early probably my
first larger format rainbow hologram and
it was called sendera and it was a
fairly pivotal piece for me and from
there I be
operate those kinds of images inside and
then subsequent to that I began to then
when I began to understand what it was
to sculpt the energy then I would work
on projects that were involved with some
kind of a special effect
to call animation or something
and then incorporate that into the scene
with this with the sculptural subjects
and then the next step was to break
through the film plane and then to begin
sculpting in front of the plane with the
light where the solid object now they
finished sculpture interrelates to the
light sculptures so now these have
become actual physical sculptures that
use Holograms as Optical elements in
this
do you ever feel stuck in holography
like the technology or the technique
hasn't evolved in the last 20 years you
know I I feel that in on a technical
level but but at the same time
I think that there are always reasons
for these things and one of them I think
is that um
when you when you have limitations and
you begin to focus on what those
limitations are
you know where the borders and the
barriers are it just gives you a
framework within to work and you stretch
that and you push aside you you push it
where you want it to go as slowly as it
or as fast as you need to go
and I and I find that it it offers
whatever context you you have your
context is usually in controlled by what
the technology will offer and that's the
space you've got to work with so you you
do it interestingly I think as far as
your work I know you could probably list
exhibits that you've had your work in
but would you like to cover some of the
exhibits that are a little bit more
meaningful to you in your memory I guess
uh holography is unique in that it's it
has always been so new and dynamic
um that it oftentimes broke down doors
that one might not normally do with
other media for example in the early
days Jody Burns
at all other people's influences well
managed to open up a showing for us at
the Museum of Modern Art
and uh very early in the game to do that
but
but at the same time a very exciting
experience it gave us a chance to just
sort of show show what we're doing
and uh so that was a for a beginner that
was an extraordinary experience and then
from there of course the many many group
shows that we've done the Museum of
holography in New York which
unfortunately is no longer there for us
uh
uh was was always there as an outlet for
viewing my work and then later on in the
travels
one of the nice things about holography
it allows you to travel some and uh and
build yourself a nice little your own
form of glamorous lifestyling but I've
had some great times in Europe and so
forth I think one of the shows that
stands
are showing Hamburg
uh Hamburg Germany
uh which was an extraordinary chance for
us at the hamburger kuns tala which is a
very reputable Art Museum and we
we enjoyed very much the sense of
continuity that we got from seeing the
very old old
classic artworks sort of bleeding into
the newer technology that was ours on
the next floor up
another extraordinary experience was uh
was the an exhibition and a conference
recently in Berlin uh headed up by
Dieter young there was it was an
extraordinary elect
about a week where scientists
mathematicians poets
magicians I as I recall I think there
was even someone there involved with
designing mirages it's an extraordinary
event it's these kinds of exciting
things that deal with holography and and
all of its accessories that you think
it's very exciting so yeah I've had
quite a few memorable travels
uh do you remember anything at all with
Salvador Dali
you remember he's actually he probably
was probably more response
response in the medium that anyone
is a laser transmission Holograms which
I believe were done by sell when lissack
back in the early days and it was my
having saved his one of his uh one of
selwyn's portraits of Salvador Dali that
they were working on at the time from
being damaged in a flood that that I was
rewarded for my Valor for having uh
saved the hologram by being given a
course in holography my first
introduction happens through Salvador
Dali actually why don't you tell
everyone where your studio is located in
New York now Studio here in Manhattan is
on the it's at 176 East Third streets
and we've been here about 10 years the
earlier location was the one that so
many people knew about underneath the
quad movie theater on 13th Street in
Manhattan but now we're on the east side
and we've got two studios here and my
partner Sam Moray of course is uh comes
and goes in his various and Sundry
activities recently having finished a
residency in Cologne Germany and
the great Passion that I have now of
course is that recently begun working
with Anna Maria Nicholson at the center
for the holographic art yes that's in
Brooklyn in Brooklyn that's in Queens
that means just across the river from
from Manhattan One Stop on the train
right near the
the new home of the Museum of Modern Art
actually in the two distance there's
going to have a temporary home near
where we are in Long Island City in
Queens
um we're in a good spot and uh and we
have our artist and residency program up
and running we're in into our second
cycle and we're
really mounting an exhibition of the
works that resulted from the first cycle
of awardees for the this program that we
have been running it's funded by the
Shearwater Foundation many thanks to
them for making this equipment available
to the holographic Community we
certain to
uh or who are listening and tuned in
know that we are excited to
holocenter.com
has guidelines for Grant proposals for
people who would like to work with pulse
lasers so it's a great opportunity to
get in there and make some Holograms
I'll make sure there's a link on the
whole us off page so people can visit
that site too that would be great you
know to me Sam's almost like a mystery
man damn yeah well Sam is a mystery man
well I've always heard the term Dan and
Sam yes well his work is extraordinary I
I think he works I've seen some pieces
of his that he combined with neon and
different things yeah yeah he he did
begin incorporating uh neon sculpture
with
with Holograms and then did some
wonderful works during that period where
he had glass plinths and
he's a very brilliant artist and was a
painter before he got involved with
photography and I I loved his painting
very much and and he he very much in my
mind exemplifies
a way a painter
into a new medium and his uh his new
medium of holography and that had an
interesting way of interpreting his
painting and he's still very active
creating Holograms absolutely yes yes
he's currently uh
actually one of the Great
ER the grants for our first cycle at the
center and which
afforded him the opportunity of making a
sculptural project which he's working on
right now so his piece will be in this
first our first opening which will be
the center for two weeks starting April
7th yes and uh from there it will travel
to Gallery in Fort Myers and then
on to the Tucson Museum of Contemporary
Art wow so
launching that show and the be a good
one that's fantastic now you offer
Workshop programs at your New York
Studios as well right yes I I have
always taught that it's been something
that I found the best
the best and also at a college in New
York as well yes I I have a course that
runs uh basic and advanced course that
runs at the School of Visual Arts here
on in lower Manhattan and this session
we have 10 great students that have been
doing some really interesting work we're
just moving now into rainbow holography
our first course deals with laser
transmission and white light reflection
and their Advanced now we're dealing
with the rainbows in their star
great secrets of that wonderful little
technology do they have a lab there and
everything right there they have a small
Lab at the at the FBA um at times when
class is this large I bring them over to
my studio
we can we can get more work done there
but but they do have a nice workable lab
there small one but but it works what do
you think of the new uh work with the
diodes the fact I'm very excited by this
I'm glad to see that you've really put
your nose to the wheel on this one uh
I'm I'm very very happy with the results
I I think I mentioned you prior to this
current conversation that I'd like to
interview you sometime oh really I'd
like to find out I'd like to find out
your Origins Etc but we'll deal with
that issue later on in any case yes the
diode lasers are a terrific terrific new
contribution I really like what it's
going to do for the beginner and I'm
even hoping uh
soon I might begin to uncover the
possibilities as a more advanced worker
in the field to use some of these diodes
to make Holograms I really hope that can
happen yeah they have a few things you
need to get used to working with them
but once you get used to them it's okay
well that's true of everything isn't it
yes it is true yeah yeah what's the
latest work that you're working on now
the uh the current what I'm doing right
now is uh I'm working on
the next in a series of works that I
call the sleeper series
I have an odd way of working sometimes I
work differently each time but I do like
to work with special effects and uh and
there is a current work that I'm doing
where I'm dealing with an optical
animation
where uh where an image will appear to
move in a situation of course in
holography where you can't have anything
moving of course yes so I will take for
example a
an object that might look in in the case
of the one that I'm thinking of is not
the current one but a prior one the one
I'm thinking of which was the the
original subject was a kitchen dish
drainer you know the slats and
horizontal lines and I have this little
thing I call my my time machine which is
a a large parabolic mirror made of metal
with a dent in it that I'm giving away
my secret here
but the the way that the dent reflects
the the
um the flat
moving are the flat slots causes it to
distort in such a way that it actually
literally turns it into a spinning disc
oh really and it's an Exquisite feeling
the way the light moves As you move from
left to right and what I've done is I've
taken that little dent and then removed
removed all of the
context from it so that it just appears
to be a swirling bit of light and it
turns out to look very much like a
flying saucer I have completed a large
format when I actually at John John
Perry studio where he was so helpful in
helping me make this spinning disc
project about maybe seven feet into the
room oh my goodness with a nice blue sky
White Cloud background and I hadn't
quite I haven't quite figured out where
I want to take it from there these
things sometimes take time and study
yeah but it's a very exciting idea to uh
to be able to make projected images of
moving it is what I consider to be
sculpting sculpting energy and there's
something away I've always had a
fascination with the way light behaves
of course as I think a lot of us have
and uh so I do things like if you if you
if you understand that a lens will flop
an image in One Direction and then
perhaps in another you know why you have
to load your slides backwards yeah I got
very interested for example in that
little that little moment of time over
which it travels
flopping into horizontal in the vertical
Direction and I decided to image that
using laser light with simply because it
stays in focus to Infinity in the way
that I've set it up and so if I capture
that moving image on a piece of frosted
glass I discovered that I could make an
animation of it and
Photography they call it the circle of
confusion I think I might have mentioned
that
and as it turns out it's my own sort of
rendering of the way uh light behave and
as you move from left to right in front
of the Hologram the light will tumble
and fall towards you through the film
plane and then beyond your shoulder oh
my goodness so it's uh
it's kind of what I want to do is
involve the viewer in the activity of
the Hologram itself I've always seen
holography as being a cinema
thing in a way I guess that's why I use
I use sort of narrative Tableau and so
forth I guess the background in theater
has a lot to do with that well these are
the Holograms that people should see
rather than the coffee cups and the
puppies yeah well it's difficult to get
them out there you know it's uh it it's
actually not difficult if one just takes
the time to show this work in the proper
way I'm so busy making work I'm really
not terribly good at getting it out
there visible I need someone to help me
with that so are you still working with
the iPhone
we are you know I'm a little bit behind
the times here we have not as yet moved
into the new possibilities for the BB
plates
um I'm looking forward to getting our
assistance out at the
for the holographic Arts to begin
testing and each time we we dedicate
ourselves to that idea we get a new air
who comes in and takes our time and we
have to go do this magic for them we
must be stockpiled with ag for stuff we
have some we have some we have enough to
get us through the uh the next uh
session I would say and then we'll have
to search for new material and I look
forward to testing the new stuff I've
heard good things about a few different
materials we just I think these things
you have to make your own and once we do
that we'll be back in gear I think yeah
yeah I have one eight by ten I have a
plate left that's all I have a bag oh
really well we have no plates but
fortunately at the center we do have a
laminating machine oh excellent so we
um although it's never easy in
holography it may be the most exciting
thing in the in the area but it is never
quite as easy as you'd like it to be so
the laminations are often faulty and we
have to go back and redo and redo and
get it right but we're working on it
when you work with artists do you seem
to get the feeling that they're
frustrated when they find out what they
can do and what they can't do with
holography
you know I I
but I think I I have a way of sort of
guiding people in the in the direction
and affording them a context in general
if I'm in charge of the situation
providing them with a context where they
begin to
the possibilities are within the
confines of the of the medium I think
probably my one failure was with Robert
rauschenberg unfortunately who I think
was a little too much all
at one day to the Museum of Photography
but uh but there have been so many
who've taken to it and in fact this
project I was just speaking with uh
Matthew Schreiber who was our current
artist in Residence this week
and he was talking about the exciting
Ventures he had with so many very
well-known artists uh with this work
that was done at the C project in uh in
Bain Florida
it's uh it's just a little bit of
translation you know it's it's part of
what you I think do and what I do is you
try and make this data workable for the
person who wishes to use it to express
himself and you try and not editorialize
their views as much as you can but at
the same time you have to guide them in
what really is feasible given the amount
of time one has to do it do you think
the argument about holography as a
legitimate medium has diminished
somewhat yeah
we're just close to it Frank we don't
understand we're not looking at this
thing from the proper perspective when
we see it that way yeah it's I think
it's just beginning I think it's just
beginning I think that
holography is an art form
began a little shaky footing and for for
for obvious reasons in the early days
the work that was being produced was not
you know it was experimental a lot of it
and a lot of times it was shown without
that information having been provided
I'm thinking of the the ICP show where
where I uh New York Times when based at
it and rightfully so but he didn't
understand the context it was not an art
show it was a show of the technological
possibilities
and that set up a sort of predisposition
not to accept holography for a short
period but as work begins to get more
and more sophisticated in the hands of
artisan as they begin to understand the
vocabulary better and better they begin
to expand their view of what the whole
of them is and how it might fit into
their artistic Vision in other words
incorporating into perhaps a larger
format perhaps into installation ideas I
I just recently got a postcard from a
absolutely beautiful beautiful piece
that I'm seeing here from Sally Weber
for example called Matrix which is
installed in in Los Angeles area I mean
this is an application of holography
that that arrives at where at where it
can be it is an extraordinarily colorful
the Magnificent
bath of
Prismatic and wonderful lighted it's
it's it's very Tastefully done uh and
and incorporates
um all sorts of
um ritualistic and technological
patterns and weeds and so forth so much
can be done with this medium and and
it's just now that artists are beginning
to really gain control of it do you
think the artists are a little bit more
embracing of Technology now because of
the digital Revolution it would seem
that it's faster wouldn't it I I feel
that for my SBA students
occasionally where where it's it's a
more instant gratification with a
computer
um but do you think that helps
holography the fact that holography is
also based on a technology well it's
very different isn't it you know yeah
analog yes it is yeah it's much more to
my eyes it's much more elegant because
it is
it's just something about working with
those
that is so magical yeah um I think well
you do you do have it in your blood
don't you well I do I think my blood is
composed mostly of light yes and hot air
as you've heard for the past 20 minutes
your blood is at 63-28
a very good way of putting it very good
way of putting it I don't live I laze
well Dan I want to thank you very much
for taking the time out of your schedule
come on the show and I'm sure people are
just happiest toast to be able to be
come onto the site and listen to you uh
talk about the work that you've done
over the years well I'm flattered that
you chose to interview me I do
appreciate it so let's just mention one
more time that exhibit that you have
coming up at your Center in Queens yes
it's the center for the holographic Arts
at 45-10 court Square in uh in Long
Island City New York just across the
river from Manhattan opening on April
7th and uh we have four of our air
recipients uh five actually counting
Margaret bennion from England it's going
to be a wonderful show we'll be there
for two weeks
going to be knighted by the queen oh
absolutely yes I just entered that into
uh we have a newsletter actually
what's going on in the Arts and I do
it's called Echo and uh not as
sophisticated as what you've got cooking
here but uh just uh I'm pleased to punch
to be able to do it and one of the
stories is about Margaret's receiving
the Her Majesty's award for her
contribution and her work in holography
which is extraordinary you see this we
have arrived yes we have we've been
ordained by Royals I told you it's all
very glamorous I think
uh why don't you take a minute to go
down the list of participants in the
show
what is it that you look for when you
receive a proposal to make someone a
successful candidate well um
where guidelines pretty much uh
what the uh okay what the guidelines are
but really all we're asking for is a
simple one-page description of the idea
and along with your your CV your your
resume uh and uh some kind of stuff and
then support materials that might help
us understand what it is that the artist
wants to achieve and then of course we
should submit all of this to the
the panelists and then they make their
selections based upon
that we receive from the artist so it's
not it's not up to us but uh that's sort
of the direction that we're looking keep
it simple
and uh you know if it's good I'm sure it
will get selected we're very grateful to
the Shearwater foundation for making
pretty much if they go to the site
they'll see it at holocenter.com okay
yeah
well Dan thank you very much I thank you
Frank okay I'll talk to you later all
right bye take care